<resources>
    <string name="app_name">BD Division</string>
    <string name="txt1">"The administration of Bangladesh is divided into eight major regions called divisions (বিভাগ bibhag).
        Each division is named after the major city within its jurisdiction that also serves as the administrative headquarters of that division.
        Each division is further split into several districts (জেলা jela) which are then further sub-divided into Upazilas (উপজেলা upôjela)."</string>
    <string name="txt2">"Following the independence of Bangladesh in 1971, the country had four divisions: Chittagong Division, Dhaka Division, Khulna Division and Rajshahi Division.
In 1983, the English spelling of the Dacca Division (along with the name of the capital city) was changed into Dhaka to more closely match the Bengali pronunciation.
In 1993, Barisal Division was split off from Khulna Division; in 1995, Sylhet Division was split off from Chittagong Division; and in 2010 (25 January), Rangpur Division was split off from Rajshahi Division.
        In terms of area the newly formed Rangpur Division ranked fifth followed by Barisal and Sylhet division.
On 14 September 2015 Mymensingh Division was added as eighth division.
        In 2015 there started process to create two more divisions, Comilla Division and Faridpur Division."</string>

    <string name="dhaka1">"Dhaka (Bengali: ঢাকা, pronounced: [ɖʱaka]; English /dɑːkɑː/ DAH-kah, /dɑːkə/ DAH-kuh, or /dækə/ DACK-uh) is the capital and largest city of Bangladesh.
        It is one of the world's most populated cities, with a population of 17 million people in the Greater Dhaka Area.[4][8]
        It is also 3rd densely populated city in the world.
        Located in an eponymous district and division, it lies along the east bank of the Buriganga River in the heart of the Bengal delta.
        The city is a microcosm of the entire country, with diverse religious and ethnic communities.
        Dhaka is the economic, cultural and political centre of Bangladesh.
        Its name was romanised as Dacca until the current spelling was adopted in 1983.[9]
        It is the largest city in the Bengal region.
        It is also a major city of South Asia and among the OIC states."</string>
    <string name="dhaka2">"The origins of the name for Dhaka are uncertain.
        Once dhak tree was very common in the area and the name may have originated from it.
        Alternatively, this name may refer to the hidden goddess Dhakeshwari, whose shrine is located in the south-western part of the city.[15]
        Another popular theory states that Dhaka refers to a membranophone instrument, dhak which was played by order of Subahdar Islam Khan I during the inaugurating of the Bengal capital in 1610.[16]
        Some references also say that it was derived from a Prakrit dialect called Dhaka Bhasa; or Dhakka, used in the Rajtarangini for a watch-station; or it is the same as Davaka,
        mentioned in the Allahabad pillar inscription of Samudragupta as an eastern frontier kingdom.[17]"</string>

    <string name="dhaka3">"Dhaka is located in central Bangladesh at 23°42′N 90°22′E, on the eastern banks of the Buriganga River.
        The city lies on the lower reaches of the Ganges Delta and covers a total area of 300 square kilometres (120 sq mi).[44]
        Tropical vegetation and moist soils characterize the land, which is flat and close to sea level.
        This leaves Dhaka susceptible to flooding during the monsoon seasons owing to heavy rainfall and cyclones.[45]
        Dhaka District is bounded by the districts of Gazipur, Tangail, Munshiganj, Rajbari, Narayanganj, Manikganj."</string>
    <string name="ctg1">"Chittagong /tʃɪtəɡɒŋ/ (Bengali: চট্টগ্রাম Bengali pronunciation: [tʃɔt̠t̠ɔgram], Chatga) is a major coastal seaport city and financial centre in southeastern Bangladesh.
        The city has a population of more than 2.5 million[1] while the metropolitan area has a population of over 6.5 million,[5] making it the second largest city in the country.
        It is the capital of an eponymous district and division. The city is located on the banks of the Karnaphuli River between the Chittagong Hill Tracts and the Bay of Bengal.
        Much of Chittagong Division is located within the ecological Indo-Burma zone on the boundary of the India Plate and Burma Plate.
        This makes Chittagong the crossroads of the Indian subcontinent and Southeast Asia.
        The port city has been known by various names in history, including Chatigaon, Chatigam, Chattagrama, Islamabad, Chattala, Chaityabhumi and Porto Grande De Bengala"</string>
    <string name="ctg2">"Stone age fossils and tools unearthed in the region indicate that Chittagong has been inhabited since Neolithic times.[15] It is an ancient port city, with a recorded history dating back to the 4th century BCE.[16] Its harbour was mentioned in Ptolemy's world map in the 2nd century as one of the most impressive ports in the East.[17] The region was part of the ancient Bengali Samatata and Harikela kingdoms. The Candra dynasty once dominated the area, and was followed by the Varman dynasty and Deva dynasty.
Chinese traveler Xuanzang described the area as "a sleeping beauty rising from mist and water" in the 7th century.[18]
Arab Muslim traders frequented Chittagong since the 9th century. In 1154, Al-Idrisi wrote of a busy shipping route between Basra and Chittagong, connecting it with the Abbasid capital of Baghdad.[12]
Many Sufi missionaries settled in Chittagong and played an instrumental role in the spread of Islam.[19]
Sultan Fakhruddin Mubarak Shah of Sonargaon conquered Chittagong in 1340,[20] making it a part of Sultanate of Bengal. It was the principal maritime gateway to the kingdom, which was reputed as one of the wealthiest states in the Indian subcontinent. Medieval Chittagong was a hub for maritime trade with China, Sumatra, the Maldives, Sri Lanka, the Middle East and East Africa. It was notable for its medieval trades in pearls,[21] silk, muslin, rice, bullion, horses and gunpowder. The port was also a major shipbuilding hub.
Ibn Battuta visited the port city in 1345.[22] Niccolò de' Conti from Venice also visited around the same time as Battuta.[23] Chinese admiral Zheng He's treasure fleet anchored in Chittagong during imperial missions to the Sultanate of Bengal."</string>

    <string name="ctg3">"Chittagong lies at 22°22′0″N 91°48′0″E. It straddles the coastal foothills of the Chittagong Hill Tracts in southeastern Bangladesh.
        The Karnaphuli River runs along the southern banks of the city, including its central business district.
        The river enters the Bay of Bengal in an estuary located 12 kilometres (7.5 mi) west of downtown Chittagong.
        Mount Sitakunda is the highest peak in Chittagong District, with an elevation of 351 metres (1,152 ft).[43]
        Within the city itself, the highest peak is Batali Hill at 85.3 metres (280 ft).
        Chittagong has many lakes that were created under Mughal rule.
        In 1924, an engineering team of the Assam Bengal Railway established the Foy's Lake.[43]"</string>
<string name="syllet1">"Sylhet /sɪlhət/, also known as Jalalabad, is a metropolitan city in northeastern Bangladesh.
    It is the administrative seat of Sylhet Division. The city is located on the right bank of the Surma River in northeastern Bengal.
    It has a subtropical climate and lush highland terrain.
    The city has a population of more than 479,837 residents.[5]
    Sylhet is one of Bangladesh's most important spiritual and cultural centers.It is one of the most important city of Bangladesh just after Dhaka and Chittagong because of many reasons like economy,tourism etc.
    The city's dargahs draw several thousand devotees each year."</string>
    <string name="syllet2">"Sylhet was under the realm of the Harikela and Kamarupa kingdoms of ancient Bengal and Assam.
        Buddhism was prevalent in the first millennium.
        In the early medieval period, the area was dominated by Hindu principalities, which were under the nominal suzerainty of the Senas and Devas.
        The history of the dynasts in the region is documented by their copper-plate charters.
        The 14th century marked the beginning of Islamic influence in Sylhet. The Muslim general Shamsuddin Firoz Shah's army defeated the local Hindu Raja Gour Govinda after the raja's persecution of Muslim migrants. The general's army was aided by a Middle Eastern Sufi missionary, Shah Jalal, and 313 of his companions.[18] The area became known as Jalalabad (Land of Jalal) under the Bengal Sultanate. It hosted a mint which produced the taka. When the Moroccan traveler Ibn Batutta visited Shah Jalal in Sylhet in 1345, he noted that the locals embraced Islam due to Shah Jalal's missionary activities.
        "It was by his labours that the people of these mountains became converted to Islam" wrote Battuta in his diary.
        Bengali Muslims were exploiting the fertile land of Sylhet for agricultural production and enjoyed relative prosperity.The region began to experience an influx of Muslim settlers, including Turks, Arabs and Persians.
        During the late 16th century, the region was largely controlled by the Kingdom of Bhati. The Mughals subsequently conquered the region. Sylhet became a district headquarter of the Bengal Subah.
        Its eight mahals included Pratapgarh, Bahua, Jaintia, Habili, Sarail, Laur and Harinagar.
        The district generated annual revenues of 167,000 rupees."</string>
    <string name="syllet3">"Sylhet is located at 24.8917°N 91.8833°E, in the north eastern region of Bangladesh within the Sylhet Division, within the Sylhet District and Sylhet Sadar Upazila. Sylhet has a typical Bangladesh tropical monsoon climate (Köppen Am) bordering on a humid subtropical climate (Cwa) at higher elevations. The rainy season from April to October is hot and humid with very heavy showers and thunderstorms almost every day, whilst the short dry season from November to February is very warm and fairly clear.
        Nearly 80% of the annual average rainfall of 4,200 millimetres (170 in) occurs between May and September."</string>
    <string name="raj1">"Rajshahi (Bengali: রাজশাহী; historically Rampur Boalia; nicknamed Silk City) is a metropolitan city in Bangladesh and a major urban, commercial and educational centre of North Bengal. It is the administrative seat[note 1] of Rajshahi Division  Rajshahi District . Located on the north bank of the Padma River, near the Bangladesh-India border; the city has a population of over 763,952 residents.[3] The city is surrounded by satellite towns like Katakhali  Nowhata, which together build an urban agglomeration of about 1 million population.
Modern Rajshahi lies in the ancient region of Pundravardhana. The foundation of the city dates to 1634, according to epigraphic records at the mausoleum of Sufi saint Hazrat Shah Makhdum. The area hosted a Dutch settlement in the 18th century.[4] The Rajshahi municipality was constituted during the British Raj in 1876. It was a divisional capital of the Bengal Presidency."</string>
    <string name="raj2">"Rajshahi district was a part of the Pundra region of ancient Bengal. The capital of Vijay Sen, the king who led military operations in Sri Lanka and Southeast Asia was located 9 miles (14 km) to the west of Rajshahi town. In medieval times, the region came to be known as "Rampur Boalia". The origin of the present name of "Rajshahi" is debated among scholars. Most say that it takes its name from Hindu Kings and zamindars (or "Rajas") as Raj and the persianised Shahi; both of which means Royal or Kingdom.[6] The administrative district was established in 1772 and the municipal corporation in 1876. Rajshahi was dominated by various Maharajas, Rajas and Zamindars.[7]"</string>
    <string name="raj3">"Geographically Rajshahi is situated within Barind Tract, 23 m (75 ft) above sea level  lies at 24°22′26″N 88°36′04″E.The city is located on the alluvial planes of the Padma river, which runs through southern side of the city. It is bounded on the east, north and west by Paba Upazila (subdivision of a district) of the district."</string>
    <string name="khul1">"Khulna (Bengali: খুলনা ) is the third-largest city in Bangladesh.[4] It is the administrative seat of Khulna District and Khulna Division. As of the 2011 census, the city has a population of 663,342.[5]
Khulna is an old river port located on the Rupsha River. It is an important hub of Bangladeshi industry and hosts many national companies. It is served by Port of Mongla, the second largest seaport in the country. It is also one of the two principal naval command centres of the Bangladesh Navy. Navy base BNS Titumir is located in the city."</string>
    <string name="khul2">"Khulna was part of the ancient kingdoms of Vanga or Samatata. In the 12th century, it came under the Sena dynasty during the reign of Ballal Sena and formed part of the Bagri division of Bengal. The previous name of this region was Jalalabad.
During the 14th century, Shamsuddin Firoz Shah became the first Muslim ruler to arrive in the city. The Muslim settlements in the city increased during the time of Shamsuddin Ilyas Shah. Subsequently, many mosques and shrines began to be established. In the 15th century, a Muslim saint named Khan Jahan Ali acquired a jagir (fiefdom) comprising a large part of the greater Khulna Division from the king of Gauḍa. Later he started to exercise full rights of sovereignty and continued to do so till his death in 1459.[8]"</string>
    <string name="khul3">"Khulna is the 3rd largest city after Dhaka and Chittagong. Khulna is located in south-western Bangladesh at 22°49′0″N 89°33′0″E, on the banks of the Rupsha and Bhairab river. It covers a total area of 59.57 km2,[10] while the district itself is about 4394.46 km2. It lies south of Jessore and Narail, East of Satkhira, West of Bagerhat and North of the Bay of Bengal. It is part of the largest delta in the world. In the southern part of the delta lies the Sundarban, the world's largest mangrove forest. The city of Khulna is in the northern part of the district, and is mainly an expansion of trade centres close to the Rupsha and Bhairab rivers. The Mayur River forms the western boundary of the metropolitan area."</string>
    <string name="bar1">"Barisal (Bengali: বরিশাল Bariśāl; historically Bakla-Chandradwip; also Gird-e-Bandar) is a major city that lies on the bank of Kirtankhola river in south-central Bangladesh. It is the largest city and the administrative headquarter of both Barisal district and Barisal Division. It is one of the oldest municipalities and river ports of the country. Barisal municipality was established in the year 1876 during the British Raj and upgraded to City Corporation on 25 July 2002.[4] The city consists of 30 wards and 50 mahallas with a population of 328,278 according to the 2011 national census. The area of the city is 58 km².[5]"</string>
    <string name="bar2">"Barisal was a semi-independent area in the Mughal period because of heavy fighting between them and Hindu chiefs. In course of time, it fell under the Bengal Nawabs, the last being Raja Nakuleswar Bose and then colonial British India, later passed to East Pakistan at independence and finally Bangladesh.
The central city of this region is the city of Barisal. It is one of the biggest river ports in Bangladesh. It is a city with nearly 0.38 million people and a divisional headquarters, medical college, cadet college, some pharmaceutical industries, textile industries and the Bangladesh Inland Water Transport Authority's head office. Barisal is fast growing city of the country stands on the Kirtankhola River. Country's first short landing and take off airport has been completed in Barisal and a private Airlines named Air Bengal has begun its regular air flight between Dhaka Tejgaon Airport and Barisal.
The city is sometimes called the "Venice of the East" or the "Venice of Bengal"
    </string>
    <string name="bar3">"Barisal city occupies an area of 58 km2.
Barisal District, with an area of 2790.51 km2, is bounded by Madaripur, Shariatpur, Chandpur and Lakshmipur districts on the north, Patuakhali, Barguna and Jhalokati districts on the south, Bhola and Lakshmipur districts on the east, Jhalokati, Pirojpur and Gopalganj districts on the west. Several rivers flow across Barisal including the Kirtankhola, Arial Khan, Khoyrabad, Kalijira and Sandha."</string>
<string name="my1">"Mymensingh (/maɪmɛnsiːŋ/; Bengali: ময়মনসিংহ [mɔe̯mɔnʃiŋɦɔ]), formerly called Nasirabad,[3] is a city in Mymensingh District in central region of Bangladesh, situated on the Brahmaputra river. It is also the district headquarters. Mymensingh is the anglicised pronunciation of the original name Momenshahi, referring to a ruler called Momen Shah.[4] The cadet college established in Tangail in 1963 was called Momenshahi Cadet College.[5] The city is known for educational institutions like Bangladesh Agricultural University, Mymensingh Polytechnic Institute Mymensingh Medical College, Jatiya Kabi Kazi Nazrul Islam University, Mymensingh Engineering College, Mymensingh Ananda Mohan College, Mymensingh Zilla School, Mymensingh Girls' Cadet College, Mymensingh Muminunnesa Women's College, Premier Ideal High School, Vidyamoyee Govt. Girls' High School, Women Teachers Training College, Mymensingh Engineering College, Notre Dame College,Mymensingh and Shahid Syed Nazrul Islam College. Other landmark institutions include Mymensingh Army Cantonment. Also it is related with old Brahmaputra river, handcrafted duvet called Nakshikantha (Bengali: নকশীকাঁথা) and a rural ballad called Maimansingha Gitika. Mymensingh city is located about 120 km (75 mi) north of Dhaka which is the capital of the country."</string>
    <string name="my2">"Mymensingh is one of the 16 old districts of Bangladesh which was constituted by the British East India Company on 1 May 1787.[6] Being more than 220 years old, Mymensingh has a rich cultural and political history. At the beginning Begunbari was chosen as the headquarters of the district. However the district headquarters was relocated to Mymensingh when Begunbari devastated by flash flood. Earlier northern Mymensingh was part of Muazzamabad and south Mymensingh was called Nasirabad.[7] During the British Raj most of the inhabitants of the town were Hindus.
From the early 20th century Muslims moved into town. Since then this city has played an important role as a centre for secularism. The Vidyamoyee Uccha Balika Bidyalaya and Muminunnesa Women's College have played a great role in educating Bengali Muslim women. A majority of first-generation successful Bangladeshi women have attended these schools and colleges, including the first woman justice of the High Court of Bangladesh, Justice Nazmun Ara Sultana.[8] However, many Hindu families left Bangladesh during the partition of India in 1947. A second spell of exodus took place following the Indo-Pak war of 1965. Many people born and raised Mymensingh have left for West Bengal since the 1960s. The exodus continues albeit at a slower pace."</string>
    <string name="my3">"The climate of Mymensingh is moderate, much cooler than Dhaka, as it is closer to the Himalayas. The monsoon starts in May or June and continues till August. It rains heavily and sometimes for days and weeks. During the monsoon, the temperature varies between 15 and 20 degrees. The temperature falls below 15 °C (59 °F) in winter which is spread over December and January and may well include November and February. The highest temperature is felt during April–May period, when the temperature may be as high as 40 °C (104 °F). High humidity causes heavy sweating during this period. For western travellers, the best time to visit is between November and February."</string>
    <string name="rang1">"Rangpur Division (Bengali: রংপুর বিভাগ) was formed on 25 January 2010,[1] as Bangladesh's 7th division. Before that, it had been the northern eight districts of the Rajshahi Division. The Rangpur division consists of eight districts. There are 58 Upazilas or subdistricts under these eight districts. Rangpur is the northernmost division of Bangladesh and has a population of 15,665,000 at the 2011 Census"</string>
    <string name="rang2">"Mansingh, commander of Emperor Akbar, conquered part of Rangpur in 1575. Rangpur came completely under the Mughal empire in 1686. Mughalbasa and Mughalhat of Kurigram district still bear marks of the Mughal rule in the region. During the Mughal rule part of Rangpur was under the sarkar of Ghoraghat, and part under the sarkar of Pinjarah.[2] Rangapur Ghoraghat has been mentioned in the Riyaz-us-Salatin. During the early period of the company rule Fakir-Sannyasi Rebellion and peasant rebellion were held in Rangpur."</string>
    <string name="rang3">"Rangpur division has road, rail, and air connections to other divisions as well as the capital. There are 21 express trains from this division to communicate with the other part of the country. There are three airports in this division among them major airport is in Saidpur Airport Saidpur."</string>
</resources>
